[SPEAKER_00]: It seems to be, well, it's a nice practice, somehow easier.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not so confusing, like, just watching the state of your mind, and then just being honest.
[SPEAKER_00]: By seeing the state of your mind, you don't lose the perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, where does this go?
[SPEAKER_00]: When you don't see the state of your mind, why do you go with it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you know it might end in... that will most likely... well, more certainly end in pain, and displeasure, and disappointment, or whatever, you kind of go ahead with it, because you don't... you haven't maintained a perspective to seeing that it's your general state of mind that was directing you there, not that particular thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, it is relatively easy if the person is honest.
[SPEAKER_01]: But obviously, you know, different people can find different things easier in terms of practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is, like, it's not...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think, as we spoke yesterday, it's not just, oh, just watch your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't really make sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it makes sense, but it's so general that it doesn't really make a difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, watch your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, what can you mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's the... when we spoke yesterday, like, when we said watching the state of your mind means watching the background of your mind, which is what citta is, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that peripheral, the general, like, mood, cloud, whatever we called it in the past, that kind of just like a general sort of leaning towards certain directions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, that's how you can see the mind in terms of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, as we spoke, kind of the most obvious defilements.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, oh, like, am I not
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't have any particular sensual desire right here, right now, in front of me, exciting or disturbing me, but the background of my mind is sort of affected by that.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's like a cloud of sensuality, big, heavy in the background, nothing particularly manifested, but it's there, kind of directing me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if people are not mindful of that, they'll end up
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, particularizing that very, like, general cloud of sensuality or ill-will, like, they just feel in a bad mood, so they take it out on somebody eventually, if they're very unrestrained.
[SPEAKER_01]: If they're a bit more restrained, they won't take it on anybody else, but then they've just been in an ill-will-like mood internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's all coming from the general, kind of, peripheral, sort of,
[SPEAKER_01]: background of your particular experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's where the mind is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you never...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just watch your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Usually, people is all just looking at what's right in front of them, which means they directly don't see what their mind is, because the mind is not there in front.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind is the background of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the moods, all of those are, like, kind of a manifestation of that mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if somebody keeps an eye on the general, sort of, cloud of one's mind, that ambiguous, sort of,
[SPEAKER_01]: Pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, it's sometimes pleasant, sometimes elated, sometimes depressed, sometimes... All those are like phenomena in the same sense as you have things arising in front of your eyes, arising on their own, ceasing, persisting.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, the internal phenomenon of your of your general mind, that ambiguous one, arises in the same manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you haven't asked for... for elated mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just arose like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now it's present.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's persisting like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And while it's persisting in the state of elation, if you're mindful of it, you won't be taken by that.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't discern that phenomenon of that mind for what it is, you will be taken.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you'll be elated.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, inexplicably, inexplicably, but you'll be all over the place, because you're in a great mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything is good.
[SPEAKER_01]: All the nothing has changed, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was just your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But because you... you
[SPEAKER_01]: You have no insight, or rather, you have no capacity, but to not take it as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to take it as yours, because you don't know anything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you are related.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you're all affected, and everybody's in the same sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: When that mind, that relation ceases, and then, another state, another mind arises, a mind of ill-will, or a mind of depression, or a mind of something, then, you're completely taken by that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, you're completely
[SPEAKER_01]: When it's elated, you know it is elated.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he's depressed, you know he's depressed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's actually enough to not be taken away.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like the practice of satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows his mind is expanded.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows his mind is shrunk.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows his mind is elated.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows his mind is depressed.
[SPEAKER_01]: If he's depressed, he knows he's depressed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not I'm being depressed.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the presence of a depressed mind is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, the presence of a different elated mind is there afterwards.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's basically... and it's not... and also, that's another assumption to assume that it's
[SPEAKER_01]: Because all you're going to have is a state of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your experience will always reveal your mind through a state.
[SPEAKER_01]: And those states are different.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, those minds are minds.
[SPEAKER_01]: Brutal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not at the same time, but basically,
[SPEAKER_01]: Presence of one mind, in that the utmost general level, means such and such mind is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, another presence of a different mind, opposite to that, means such and such mind is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's all you can truly know.
[SPEAKER_01]: You assume that it's the same mind that induces those states.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when you see that there is no mind being discerned without those states given beforehand, you realize, oh, the mind is inseparable from those states.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, the mind cannot be on its own, independent of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's the same sense with the feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the Buddha said, do you take feelings to be yours?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, well, which one do you take then to be yours?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is pleasant feeling, there is unpleasant feeling, there is neither pleasant nor pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're completely different feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Separate, different feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's no one feeling that then gets, kind of, eh... turned into the colors of pleasure, then colors of displeasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a different feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Entirely different feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they don't mix.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't, like, connect.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't mold into each other.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you have three different feelings, which one is yours, then?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you have, like, millions of manifestations of your mind, which one is yours?
[SPEAKER_01]: None.
[SPEAKER_01]: None can be yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can see that, in general, the mind is, say, taken by a longing of yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Genuinely, well, I should say,
[SPEAKER_01]: Not taken by longing, because that implies the mind sits there, but you can see that the mind, which is a general, is the longing mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the depressed mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the happy mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the even mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the equanimous mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's this mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mind is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you see it as dependent, or rather as inseparable from the state it has arisen, well, you see that it's coming from over there, not from over here, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you are just sort of mindful of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just arises, ceases and persists while it changes, as any other phenomenon does.
[SPEAKER_01]: It shares exactly the same nature, but on that general level.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you have to abandon those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: When I say abandon, if you see, if you know that this longing, you know, you have a longing mind, abandon longing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, see, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: You abandon longing, sure, but you don't abandon longing by interfering with the longing mind, because that wasn't yours to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you can abandon you appropriating the longing, the mind that longs, the mind that's sad, the mind that's happy.
[SPEAKER_01]: You abandon that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You abandon the appropriation of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's a very different thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you say, oh, yes, you abandon the longing mind...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you say you abandon the longing mind, that means, like, oh, you must remove the longing from your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, basically, the mind is that longing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, removing longing from your mind means you still assume that the mind is separate from that longing, and then this longing just infected it, and then you clear it out, and then the pure mind stays.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the pure mind is the mind that's left alone.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: The pure mind is the mind which you don't get involved in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you basically discern the impossibility of your involvement in the first place, which is how you cannot... which is how you stop being involved.
[SPEAKER_00]: What about seeing the position in regard to the mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: Your position.
[SPEAKER_00]: Meaning?
[SPEAKER_00]: You see a mind as the background, and everything else is more particular.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you see you're not the background.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that would allow a citizen stepping away from the background of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, it could help.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because usually people, by not seeing that, they're taken by that background,
[SPEAKER_01]: kind of magnetic cloud, it sort of directs them towards ideal will, or sensuality, or whatever hindrance arose, or through, like, elated, super mood, happy, joyful, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's basically completely dependent on an afterly, randomly, circumstantially manifested mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's how you can basically be mindful throughout the day, regardless of where you are, what you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, not completely what you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to practice restraint, obviously.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, I mean, like, whatever you're doing, then it's not clearly unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just by keeping that peripheral eye on that general state of your mind, for what it is, you, you already, basically, you're already fortified against that, that, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Pressure that that mind would exert on you to do particular things, so that the mind, like a general cloud of, like, sensual craving,
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're not, if you're not seeing it for what it is, as a phenomenon, it will eventually pressure you into particularizing that very craving through either, you know, engaging through any sensuality that you can get at the time, wherever you were.
[SPEAKER_01]: Be it food, music, entertainment, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You end up going towards that because it pushed you there because you haven't been, you haven't been fortified in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for as long as you remind, like, oh, it's still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, three hours later of you doing whatever, you look, oh, that central mind, it's still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it stays forever, it's still in common.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know that it will have to cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it might, like, last forever, infinitely, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no end in sight when you look at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the fact that it's arising, it manifests, means that's why it will cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, infinite things are eternal.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will come to an end, with their infinity.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when the new thing arises, new mind arises, new infinity arises, and that infinity is also impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like two completely different domains.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, and I was thinking that everything has... well, these things that arise, always arise with a sense of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they arise with the infinity.
[SPEAKER_01]: They arise because there's no... there's no end in sight.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no end in terms of the possibilities.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no end.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what's mistaken as forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: But actually, you can have an infinite range of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, that's taken away.
[SPEAKER_01]: That you don't have an infinite range of things anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's how infinity is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, I think I said that in one of my answers.
[SPEAKER_01]: If, basically, if a person would be able to discern infinite,
[SPEAKER_01]: From permanent... Or see... Well, discern the difference and then you will recognize, ah, actually, permanence comes from me, the assumption of permanence, the assumption of forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Infinite... it's kind of... everything is infinite in that sense, because everything arises with, like, infinite amount of possibilities.
[SPEAKER_01]: When it arises, but when it ceases... it ceases with infinite amount of possibilities.
[SPEAKER_01]: And a new thing is manifested, or rather, a different thing is manifested also.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, everything arises in that, like, infinite structure of possibilities, like infinite mind, infinite permutations.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, there's no end to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can be seeking out and trying to encompass them all, and you won't.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you always will be more, and there'll always be more, to more, and more, to more, and more, to more, until it ceases.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the whole thing, the entire domain, the entire domain of infinity, from the past all the way into the future, that's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: That ceases.
[SPEAKER_01]: On a particular level, yeah, things last forever, in that sense, in that infinite sense, until they cease, on the general level, which is where they cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it's another mistake to look for impermanence in actual, like, in actual
[SPEAKER_01]: Cessation of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you look for them and you want to see their destruction and go, ah, that's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just another arisen thing with infinite possibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just witnessing a phenomenon, an arisen phenomenon of destruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why I mean, when I say before, or I say often, things are not impermanent because you see them cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things are impermanent because they have arisen in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, their manifestation means that's why they're not in your control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they are manifesting.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't even conceive you creating anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: You manifesting anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even when you think of you creating something, if you look closely, whatever you are kind of working with in your mind, in terms of you, that was given beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you always come in second.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, it's so.
[SPEAKER_00]: Abandoning defilements of mind, whichever defilement, you abandon it by not taking it as yours anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, just before you go further, defilements will basically refer then to the whole range of that generally affected peripheral cloud, the background of your mind, that's affected by your sensuality, all the way up into
[SPEAKER_01]: Particular push, that's pushing in a particular direction, or, you know, those... finding something like a... like a... like a particular manifestation of that general pressure, like vague ambiguous central craving that you find.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: You sort of centralize in this particular thing, or that particular thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that whole range will be defined.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can start saying no to these particular things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is the first step.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you should do that only so that you can then start discerning the phenomenon of your mind, a reason on its own, being affected by such and such unwholesome state.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you just go around denying the things in front of you, fine, but you're carrying the very source of the problem with you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not addressing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you don't get involved with that...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, seeing it for what it is, seeing, grasping that sign of that phenomenon, of that mind that has arisen in such-and-such way, means you're not getting involved, because you get involved by not seeing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why the first... well, not the first, but one of the requisites, pre-requisite for Sotāpārthi, as Janabiru mentioned, was grasping the sign of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: cittanimitta, like grasping that phenomenon of that ambiguous, vague cloud of the mind for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not over-defining it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, this is what my mind is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just seeing it for what it is, the way it has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you start seeing it for, like, the way it has arisen on its own, and not, not adding more to it, not taking away from it, then, that phenomenon, because it's seen for what it is, can then be understood as, as, as not mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But whenever there is a form of involvement, then that means appropriation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you add something to it, if you take away from it, means you still assume that you can add something to it, that you can take away something.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are involved.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, you're not seeing the clear sign of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, you have to make it clearer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you see it for what it is?
[SPEAKER_01]: Arising, ceasing, persisting or changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, persisting or changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because arising is persisting or changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ceasing away is persisting or changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, just basically seeing the given state of mind as not yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and you have to see that repetitively, like repetitively, on and on, because your first day, you get a clearer picture, you might see it first time, but then you're like, oh, I saw it once and that was it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you have to keep seeing it, and seeing it, and seeing it, for how long?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it depends how well established the assumption of mind was, in regard to that mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: For some people it's more, for some people it's less.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I think, given that it's two and a half millennia since
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha died and the kind of pure dhamma disappeared.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's probably more for all the people.
[SPEAKER_01]: They need to do lots of undoing for those assumptions to disappear.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, again, the universal principles of dhamma, the path that the Buddha himself only discovered, did not create, is always there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if there's no Buddha around, no dhamma around, if somebody's repeating these things correctly, they would reach the same goal.
[SPEAKER_01]: They would, apparently, procreation.
[SPEAKER_01]: They would see mind for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, and then, they would say that, and say, like, um, like, even purtutian view, people who don't have the right view, who never heard, like, who are not established in the right discipline, right disposition, and so on, uh, even they could actually experience this passion, this enchantment towards this body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, I mean, we see bodies disgusting, oozing, uh, getting sick, liable to misfortune, just anything, and then see other people dying, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you dwell on it long enough, you will experience revulsion and disenchantment and disappearance of passion in regard to your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's hard, and it's almost impossible, without the right view and the right instruction, to experience the same disenchantment towards your own mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, in the same sense, basically, you can see that you can.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that you can experience dispassion towards your mind is also a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, your body is a phenomenon towards which you can experience that dispassion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he said, it's hard to experience this special one, because the mind is much quicker, much more ambiguous, much more vague, much more fleeting, changes quickly, moves around, so you don't see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by not seeing it, you're appropriating it, and you have been appropriating it for such a long time, that it's almost, like, well, it feels almost as if impenetrable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, there is no more to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just taken for granted that the mind is mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind is mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, again,
[SPEAKER_01]: With the proper instruction, in terms of the dharmic practice, then you could start discerning even that mind as a phenomenon, no matter how quick it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Generally, it stays the phenomenon of the mind, so you don't... you're not swayed by the particular movements of the general mind, general moods, because they will always remain general.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, eventually, you can abandon even passion,
[SPEAKER_01]: Enchantment or whatever else with that as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just becomes another thing that's arising, ceasing, existing, world-changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: I never meant for this.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is it, boy?
[SPEAKER_00]: Huh?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Six.
[SPEAKER_00]: It always follows us, okay, to see if your mind has... what kind of state your mind is in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it defiled or not?
[SPEAKER_00]: If it is, abandon that defiled mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, even if it isn't abandoned,
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it's not a defilement, even if it's happiness and good mood, don't take it to be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, seeing the mind regardless of what that mind is, whether it's defiled or not defiled.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, don't entertain the defilements further, when they are present in the general mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, by all means.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's happiness, well, again, be wary of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, there's that sutta, I think,
[SPEAKER_01]: I think Sariputra, I don't know if Sariputra said, one should regard pleasure as like a painful arrow, dangerous arrow, and then pain as like a deadly.
[SPEAKER_01]: If pain is a dot, pleasure is a dot.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasure is a dot, pain is a deadly arrow, or something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sure, pleasure is not harmful, not unwholesome, but it's dangerous if you don't see your mind in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, then, when another mind comes, you won't see that either.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't, like, oh, well, you know, I look at stuff that bothers me, but I'm not going to look at stuff because it shares the same nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can abandon what bothers you only by abandoning the nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of the entire thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that thing also includes the nature of happy mind, or elated mind, or good mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you don't get taken... you don't get elated by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, elation is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Great.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't have to do anything about it, but I certainly can also not get involved with it, not get taken by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's say, like, to... when he knows his mind is unstained or undefiled, then joy arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's different.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's like a type of joy that arises when... not like the joy that comes as a kind of cloud of your mind, not as a state of your mind, but a joy that arises in regard to knowing your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, again, as Sariputta said, there is a pleasure arising in regard to not feeling any pleasure nor pain for an arahant, and that's very pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, I think that the joy of the mind is undefiled.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You should cultivate joy of knowing your mind, which is a joy that doesn't depend on the state of your mind, doesn't depend on your mind full stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's what it's... that's what I really... that's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want the joy...
[SPEAKER_00]: I want the joy part.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want...
[SPEAKER_00]: I want the defilement to be replaced.
[SPEAKER_00]: By the joy?
[SPEAKER_00]: By the joy of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can replace it with joy,
[SPEAKER_01]: You can replace both defilements and joy, joyful mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You replace that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, by abandoning that, you experience joy that doesn't depend neither on defilements, nor on your mind, nor on anything, basically, that's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why that pleasure is not unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's like the pleasure of the jhānas, similar.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because it's not unwholesome, fine, you don't have to worry about it, you can even cultivate it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's not unwholesome, because it's not underlined by by the, like, latent tendencies towards craving, towards this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's different.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a joy.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not happiness that has arisen on account of a happy mind, because the mind is erected.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a happiness that has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a happiness that has arisen in regard to knowing what mind
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, to recognizing the mind, to seeing the phenomenon of that mind, to not being moved by it, to being stronger than that mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the big heavy cloud of that mind, be it good or bad, wants to take you, wants to pressure you, wants to make you, you know, go a certain way.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will, for as long as that cloud is stronger than you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when you become stronger, you... and then it's like the simile in the Terra Terrigata, you know, it means like a mountain, and no matter what clouds and storms come, it just does not move.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't mean there are no storms and clouds coming.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the contrary, it means it just doesn't move.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's another sutra which would have said, eh... arahant... for... arahant is not overwhelmed by his mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: He is the one who overwhelms his mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: You develop in regard to... and you can only start developing in regard to your mind when you grasp the sign of that mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this is what the mind is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the nimitta of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you start developing in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not about the defilements never arising again, but it's the assumption that the defilements of mind or the mind is the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Defilements are defilements only when they're affecting you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Only when you're taken by them, when you took them...
[SPEAKER_01]: But there will still be defilements.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things that defile will still arise, but they will not defile you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a different thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You still have mud and dirt, but now you're not getting dirty by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Before, you would.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever there was mud, you were muddy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever there was dirt, you were dirty.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now you've cleaned your mind and it can't get dirty.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, again, the simile, like the lotus on top of a horrible swamp, filthy pond, not touched by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But also the... when the Buddha meets Mara, Mara always comes around.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the Mara still kept coming.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the Buddha just, like, always see him.
[SPEAKER_01]: i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: he would always discern.
[SPEAKER_01]: There wouldn't be even a remote possibility that he might not be able to see him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because he penetrated the whole nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this, for the Narada, is the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: He understood the full meaning of abandonment.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, no matter what arises, it can never defile him again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, there are no defilements.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yes, the storm clouds and stuff will keep arising, because it was arising with something to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has nothing to do with you from the start.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha said that, actually, in regard to Mara.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, well, the reason why Mara can do with people what he wants, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: push them in the directions and just make them engage in stuff,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because they take that which is his.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you go there in his domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: You yourself go in his domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you can't complain for him doing what he wants with you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You put on the suit and I think you... Well, he said... And what is it that belongs to Māra that people use?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, eye and sights, ear and sounds.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, basically everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your whole sense is everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: In and out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Belongs to Māra.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is a bit of tension, isn't it?
Eh?
[SPEAKER_01]: In the business.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because there is this...
[SPEAKER_00]: Does anger still exist in Buddha?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's not his, but it's anger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it wouldn't... like, you can't... you can't use the same designation or the same term anger.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you use it as anger for Putujana, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: A state that he's been defiled by, and it's making... and it's resulting in anger, you can't use the same for the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can say that things that would give rise to anger, still arise for the Buddha, but he's not angry.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't give rise to actual anger.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when they're out there trying to kill him and stuff, everybody would... anybody would be angry, or not a Buddha at all, or be upset, or feel ill will, but he didn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that doesn't mean that he was oblivious to what Devadatta was doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was saying, he's a foolish man.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's an idiot, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: His behavior is going to lead to, like, a long, long lasting harm for him, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he wasn't angry on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He couldn't have been.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, those defile... those things that defile are still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's Mahārāja's domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they will remain there for as long as these senses are in his body.
[SPEAKER_01]: These five aggregates don't break apart.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he reaches final nibbāna, then it's done.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's it, Rebecca?
[SPEAKER_00]: The joy.
[SPEAKER_00]: He knows that he has abandoned the state of longing and joy.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, rapture.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, his body is calm and his mind is concentrated.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't say he was...
[SPEAKER_00]: It says he's rapturous.
[SPEAKER_00]: You always get the sense of, like, delighted, you're getting all this excitement.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's not, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it's a translation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's sukha, or pity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, which was translated with rapture, but I think rapture comes from a Christian, like, concept, rapture.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the divine, you know, touches you, whatever, then you have that bodily elation of like, oh, rapture.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you can see through, like, well, you can get a glimpse of it through discerning the sign of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can see that it leads to that kind of immovability, equanimity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like indifference.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, indifference tells you you're cruel or oblivious or blind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just means nothing can move you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then that...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, again, you can also see through there, that through discernment of the phenomenon of your mind, then you start feeling content and joy that you are the one overwhelming your mind, not your mind overwhelming.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter what arises, no matter how high you are, it's always chopping up your limbs and brutalizing you in every possible way.
[SPEAKER_01]: You still overwhelm that mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That mind doesn't overwhelm you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's some like extreme development, strength and joy.
[SPEAKER_01]: And above all, you would, you would, like, well, you would know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can see that in that sutta when it comes to, like, through knowing your mind, you experience that joy and then that results automatically in a concentration.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't get concentration through watching your nostrils or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you kind of develop this concentration and kind of all... No, you get concentration through discernment of right things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by all means, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Meditate and sit cross-legged, or whatever, to discern what your mind... the sign of your mind, the clouds of your mind, the movement, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: See this phenomenon and fortify yourself in regard to it, and you'll be concentrated automatically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether you go to a village, whether you go to town, whether you sit alone, whether you live on top of a hill, your mind is established.
[SPEAKER_00]: Step one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Abandon the formless thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, I've done that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, I'll come for the next session at 2.30.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, I'll develop joy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, hold on to that joy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's have a tea break.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, come back at 2.30.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, we can continue from that joy.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll lead you to another step.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's wishful thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it would only be like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just here is a set... prescribed set of motions and little methods you do and you get there.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only set, the only the only method is develop understanding of the wrong things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when you do, it will result in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just think, because abandoning the mind, state of mind, I can say I want to abandon the defilements, but then I want I want to hold on to the to the joy, to the happiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's often why, yeah, that's often why people
[SPEAKER_01]: Experience fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, because you think, oh, well, if I... like, sure, I want to go in pain, but that means I have to give up all these joys and pleasures of the life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it threatens them.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's true.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's true.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to abandon it as your... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to abandon the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't mean that you become joyless or... That means you discover a different type of happiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's again what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, replace the household happiness, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: the happiness of sensuality, the happiness of a lay life, replace that with happiness of renunciation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And same with the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Replace the pains, the bothers, the troubles of a lay life, with pains of renunciation, of an ascetic life.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's much more wholesome, it's much more pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you know, you can stop and think about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, after being a monk for a number of years, living relatively securely and so on, maybe we can... Yeah, you know, there are obviously hardships of physical kind and all sorts of things, dangers, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing is actually comparable to stuff you had to deal with as a layperson, when you were still in the world, with the job, and in stress, and just in the swamp.
[SPEAKER_01]: The swamp of emotional issues, and duties, and burdens.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that just accumulates.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whether you're 15, 20, 30 years old, then you just keep growing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you have the burden.
[SPEAKER_01]: You lay down the burden.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, that burden extends to all the previous lives and all the ones that are in store for you if you don't get it out.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize, oh, it's actually... yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, again, teneteri gātau.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's much more pleasant here, living with these wild tigers and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: We don't mind dying next moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's just clean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Emotionally clean.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not burdening you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's free.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's freedom, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that takes time to develop.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the mind is used to the swamp of sensuality, distractions and so on, this seems like death.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why people freak out when they hear the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you were to develop and fortify your mind, and become accustomed to it, then you start seeing benefits, and it's like, oh, no, this is the freedom.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, freedom, for those who are unaware, it's basically death.
[SPEAKER_01]: They wouldn't be able to hold it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because there's nothing else to be... you only used to be involved with things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, you become intentionally dependent upon involvement.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, when there is nothing, it's just like boredom sets in, and then boredom gets replaced by a deep, deep anxiety and dread.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, quickly, find me something that will keep my mind away from me, from my own state, because I'll sink in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you know the correct path, then even then boredom... Well, there is no boredom.
[SPEAKER_01]: You go through it and it doesn't arise in me, because boredom only arises in regard to, like, accustomed levels of distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, when they are absent, then you feel bored.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, yes, a kind of like a gentle, unpleasant sort of push towards going back there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And boredom is that neutral feeling which is, when unknown, it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Actually, now, there's nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing exciting nor not exciting.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's even.
[SPEAKER_01]: But because you got used to only the excitement, that evenness is unpleasant now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you go back to the excitement.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or the depression.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or the depression, for that matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Depression is only depression in regard to things that you are depressed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's... that's again, like, when you do know that unpleasant... that neutral feeling, boredom or depression, when you know it, it's not unpleasant anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you discern it, it's quite peaceful.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it takes time to develop.
[SPEAKER_01]: To discern that criteria of what peace is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, not get scared of it and think it's... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Get scared of it, because you... you're so... you became so dependent on that, like, constant movement, constant action, constant something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Good or bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just as long as something is happening.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because otherwise, I'll just drown.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's pretty much everyone's life out there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you... if you think you're in control, well, okay, just... just... just decide to stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just decide to stop engaging, stop giving in to distraction, and then you'll see what's going to arise, and for how long you'll be able to... to hold it, to hold your determination.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the thing is, it's not really optional to do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might think, ah, well, you know, it will end in death, destruction, and terror, and dread.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stuff you fear throughout your life,
[SPEAKER_01]: That direction of that fear, that's where death is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sooner or later, you will be taken there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you might want to prepare yourself, or even if you're able to go through it beforehand, so when it arises, it doesn't concern you anymore, doesn't pertain to your being anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you extinguish it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Done.
[SPEAKER_01]: Arjan Chah's quote, die before you die.
[SPEAKER_01]: Literally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Remove the life, remove bhāva, the being, from ever before it's forcefully taken away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that means you keep living, keep coming back.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're dead.
[SPEAKER_00]: Death will be appropriated.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, death becomes another appropriation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means you haven't been, you haven't been... Well, you haven't let go of the appropriation of the five aggregates fundamentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: You will have to endure their destruction, and reappearing, and destruction, and reappearing, and destruction, and... because that's what they do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing obliges you to stay with them.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, nothing obliges you to stay with the clouds of the mind when they arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you do, because you don't know any better.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when you do know something, like, when you do know better, and you develop that better, then you're out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then the development, then developing your mind, developing states of mind, what about that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, again, you can you can use the same designation, but it means a different thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you want to say accurately, you're developing in regard to your mind, which is a development of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because even, like, if you yourself are not revolving around the general peripheral cloud of ill-will that has arisen, let's say, you'll stop entertaining any particular notions of ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through not engaging in those particular notions of ill-will, you wouldn't be fueling that cloud back.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it will arise, but it will arise less and less.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, certain things that might defile, might arise, but they will not defile.
[SPEAKER_01]: And knowing that you cannot be defiled, they cannot possibly linger in any sense of defilement.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was like...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think... was it Ananda who asked the Buddha or somebody asked Venerable Ananda?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it was Ananda who asked the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: When... oh, maybe not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Point is, somebody asked, I think, Venerable Ananda, and they said,
[SPEAKER_01]: always feels pleasure of his enlightenment all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, and then Buddha said, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, in the beginning, when somebody kind of develops to the point of arahantship, yeah, there will be that novelty of that kind of release.
[SPEAKER_01]: But after a while, they get used to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, they would feel pleasure, same pleasure of other country, only in certain instances, when they would end up in circumstances or something that would, like in the past, give rise to the defilements of anger or sensuality or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, it wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, they would recognize the same set of everything identical, but no response internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just fully extinguished internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: It cannot even
[SPEAKER_01]: Be conceived to kind of reappear again.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they feel the pleasure again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, I am indeed free.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not that they need a reminder, but when it happens, they'll feel that joy for like, oh, yeah, I remember when this used to pull me left and right.
[SPEAKER_01]: And control me for, you know, days at end.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then just walk off.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so the, like the Brahma vihāras, the kindness and so on, it's not the kindness, it's a different kind of kindness.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a different kind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, see, once again, once you grasp the sign of your mind, then you can start attending to what that sign is in different ways.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't start practicing Brahmā-dhikārasa or any other establishment of mind properly, if you don't have the sign of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But once you, like, fully established in recognizing the phenomenon of the mind, you're not even mistaking it anymore, you see it, then, yeah, then, okay, why don't you gladden that mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: That phenomenon is right in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just relax it, gladden it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why don't you regard it with love and kindness?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why don't you regard it with equanimity?
[SPEAKER_01]: Practice immovability in regard to that phenomenon of the mind, regardless of what the mind is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether it's affected by sensuality or happiness or whatever, you're not concerned anymore with a particular hindrance of that mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just looking at the nature of the sign of that mind, and that's... which is why...
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is the development of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, which is the development of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you are developing that mind, or rather in regard to that mind, once you've kind of stepped away this true discernment of that sign of the mind, and not being... not being... and like even the jhānas or whatever, when you establish your mind first, you like basically abandon the five hindrances, you put them away through discernment, and then you get established in that, and then the joy arises from that seclusion,
[SPEAKER_01]: And so on and so forth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Brahma, Vihānas, or any other type of stablishment of mind, it works the same, or rather pertains to the same levels.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't...
[SPEAKER_01]: Confused patujana, left and right, doesn't even discern what a phenomenon of that peripheral mind is, and then he practices in beings, radiating loving-kindness and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just wishful thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: They might make you feel better, but it doesn't really make any fundamental difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you're doing loving-kindness correctly, it should be resulting, eventually, in upekha, in equanimity, in complete arahantship, in movability.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you know, you visualizing, loving everyone and stuff, ain't gonna make a big difference there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're not applying it to the right place.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it needs to be applied to that framework, as Nirmala mentioned, to the framework of others.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's where the science...
[SPEAKER_01]: The framework of what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Others.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are another to yourself, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just less external other than the others.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when you start seeing your mind, or other minds, arising on their own, you realize this is like, yeah, there is an angry mind externally, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: in that person, there is an angry mind internally, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: in this person, but none of it is mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, then you apply loving-kindness, if you can use the word apply, basically you regard that phenomenon, that, that, that, that, like a sign of that mind, with loving-kindness.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are taking control of that independent mind that arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you're taking control, like, practicing certain attitudes in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not taking control by kind of repossessing it, by taking, like, by reappropriating, by making it mine, mine again.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You fully get established in that attitude of this, not just that it ain't mine, but it cannot even be mine, because if it were mine, it wouldn't have been arising on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it arises on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, I have absolutely no more doubt that it cannot be mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is basically the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you have absolutely no doubt that it cannot even be yours, even if you want to, and you can't even want to, because that would be a form of taking it up as yours, when you establish it, then, yeah, regard it with loving-kindness, or gladden it, or release it, or do this, or do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's like the... that would be the practice of samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: Establishing your mind in such a way, once you've seen it correctly, and once you've got it all out of there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yeah, that sort of seems, you know, secondary to privacy.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just...
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it will come naturally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the concentration will come as a result of that joy.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will come as a result of recognizing the mind for what it is and feeling, well, sheltered, feeling safe from it, feeling not burdened by it anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you feel joyful.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you're joyful, you feel calm, you feel calm, you feel concentrated.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what concentration is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's almost everything just
[SPEAKER_00]: We say that, yeah, it follows from that, or goes from that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Equanimity.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it needs to be... it needs to be rooted in the right view, in the right discernment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because as a practitioner, when a person hears a concentration, they have a practitioner's idea of concentration.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, if they then engage in a method, in a practice, they'll be revolving around their practitioner's idea of concentration, which means there will not be the right concentration.
[SPEAKER_01]: And samādhi, citta, imanjumikāra, like every, every aspect of the Noble Eightfold Path comes with the right view first.
[SPEAKER_01]: The right view makes it all right.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like so self-explanatory, that it's actually very hard to see.
[SPEAKER_01]: And obviously, because it's not, there is no like middle ground.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, yes, I don't see, but I can still do it rightly now.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll do everything else other than what I taught politics.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I'm not... like, I might not have the right view, but I still know how to meditate.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't make sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's rather nonsense, saying that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, like, sure, if knowing how to meditate means doing who knows what, who knows where, but not meditation the Buddha would encourage.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it needs to come with the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when there is a right view, it will come out of the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as you said yourself, oh, discerning the side of the mind, body feels calm, feeling calm, joy arises, feeling joy, concentration is established.
[SPEAKER_01]: Concentration having established, we can continue from other suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing clearly even more gets fully developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like seeing things clearly to the full extent means complete destruction of the fetters, clear insight and wisdom, pañña liberis, that's it, done.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, just, you know, just don't bother with trying to understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just stick to a prescribed method of, like, physical notions and observations of the nostrils and stuff, because it makes you feel better.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why the sole concern of somebody who still needs to be
[SPEAKER_01]: Developing the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then, that will make everything else right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how do you develop the right view?
[SPEAKER_01]: Through discernment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through discernment of what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Through discernment of what you're not well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through discernment, you can discern things by knowing what you're supposed to discern.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can know what you're supposed to discern by investigating what they might... what the options are for discernment, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like what we spoke in the other talk, or was it yesterday or the day before?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like measuring the task and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But as you can see, like what we spoke about now, in terms of the citta, nimitta and the phenomena of the mind, and like a general cloud, the mood and so on, it's not... well, it's not abstract.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that citta is both your feelings and your perception, which is what determines the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you feel, like, that mood, you might be able to even describe it in certain, like, terms of perception, but you also feel it simultaneously.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, that pressure of that mood, you can... or any mood, like, even if you can't quite define what it is, one thing you know for sure is whether it's pleasant or unpleasant, fundamentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether it's kind of okay, kind of not okay, or kind of, meh, naivety.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you start feeling it properly through discerning your mind, which is why full discerning of the mind results in complete destruction of your, like, feelings of suffering and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not, oh, I need to discern it abstractly and get my head around it and then I'll apply it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Getting your head around it rightly means applying it rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you can have, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, if, you know, you have a mind of your will, then, which is unpleasant, it is unpleasant, but then, you think by
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to get away from that unpleasant or pain, and then you want to get pleasure, so you give in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and that gives you pleasure, the mask, that's fundamental pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fundamentally, sensuality is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Remember, I was speaking about that before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, for somebody who's engaged in sensuality, when sensual desire arises,
[SPEAKER_01]: You just give in.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just go for it, for satisfaction, and it just feels... the whole thing just feels pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you find a reason to practice restraint, or the restraint is forced upon you, like you can't have your desires fulfilled.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you experience this tremendous pain, like a dart, as the suttas refer, piercing pain of... and you think,
[SPEAKER_01]: Initially, without any wisdom, everybody would think that that pain is result of me saying no to my desires.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you stick to it long enough, you start discerning that actually no.
[SPEAKER_01]: My restraint, my saying no, only made me neutral in regard to the reasoned thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what was revealed then was pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why we give in to the sensual desire, because it's so painful not to.
[SPEAKER_01]: When your mind is taken by sensuality, it's very painful to not give in.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't even consider it.
[SPEAKER_01]: On top of that, giving in, then, not just that masks that initial pierce of the sensuality, like pain, it doesn't just mask that, but then it coats it with pleasure on top of it, like satisfaction of the itch, enjoyment of the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you kind of have not just avoiding pain, but getting pleasure out of avoiding pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like a double whammy.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it's so hard to break away from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, like, the minds are so bogged down in it, that even if you were to start practicing in a straight, that whole pain that arises, you wouldn't be attributing it to sensuality, because you're so deluded.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll be thinking, no, this is coming from me saying no.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, basically, you saying yes or no should not make an emotional difference to anything you were about to do or you were doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it is making difference, means that thing is emotionally evolving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if it's emotionally evolving, means it's not wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, whatever you were about to do, just say no to yourself and see if any emotions are going to arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: If they do, means you're involved there and your restraint, your saying no, is just revealing you that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not adding anything to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not taking away anything from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, like, that that pain of restraint is not actually pain of restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's pain of sensuality that's revealed through restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you see that sufficiently enough, some people sooner, some people later, you would, you would not, like, your mind wouldn't go back, wouldn't go to that sensuality whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_01]: He could really relish and enjoy restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because restraint is like freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and results in, well, concentration.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, well, it results in escape from the whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: But by not, by, sorry, but by attributing the pain to restraint, you're always going to have, like, a romantic
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasurable, delightful notions of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now you're just grinding against through whatever sets of, like, morals and virtues that you adopted externally, but not really knowing why.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it always feels... And that's what we said.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't welcome, he doesn't delight the sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to start practicing those attitudes.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't welcome it, you don't delight in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because even if you practice the restraining, if you never ever engage
[SPEAKER_01]: In any bodily act of sensuality, through any sense, you still can entertain it in your mind for the rest of your life.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you abandon it in your mind, then automatically you won't be able to engage in it by body.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's another simile in the suttas when, like, having a... trying to light a fire with two fire sticks that were in the water.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, okay, sure, you take them out of the water first.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't light them while they're still in the river.
[SPEAKER_01]: But unless they dry outside of the water,
[SPEAKER_01]: You still wouldn't be able to light a fire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even, okay, I'm out of the water, but it's still wet.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, one's mind still remains wet even when the body is withdrawn from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind still remains wet in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the mind remains wet for as long as you're misplacing where the real pain comes from.
[SPEAKER_01]: By misplacing the real pain, you look for the pleasure in the wrong place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, consequently,
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, but it gets very confusing if you're trying to, you know, attack the mind, clear it out, adding this and adding that, fight it with kindness, destroy your... Well, you're just throwing more confusion onto the already existing pile of confusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you've got to make lists and make sure, oh, what do I do now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Discounting, doing this, doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's this, I do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it all leaves you out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're doing this in regard to that, but none of it really addresses you nor the very criteria of what made you choose to decide to do this against that in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's already affected by ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, you took it for granted that your power of decision is already right and knows the way out.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'll just do this when I do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: This makes sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, if somebody's honest and they know that, okay, I don't have a right view, thus, even what makes sense to me is not right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Necessarily.
[SPEAKER_01]: I do not know.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, you really have to stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, certainly, you certainly have to stop using the criteria of what feels right and what feels good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, basically, it's because of your feelings that you are not enlightened.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, using that as a criteria towards enlightenment is a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to use discernment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Literally, start developing discernment.
[SPEAKER_01]: What makes sense?
[SPEAKER_01]: Use your reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: Use... develop wisdom, understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, bit by bit, on top of that, you add a bit more, you build more, and it will progress.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will then result in discernment of the fundamental things, such as your feelings, your intentions, and so on, and then free you from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, all the good I ever talked about, really, fundamentally, is understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Developing understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing things clearly, he knows, he sees.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows that he knows, sees and he sees.